<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>FLUXNET | Geocomputation and Earth Observation</title>
    <link>https://geco-group.org/tag/fluxnet/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://geco-group.org/tag/fluxnet/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>FLUXNET</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Wed, 21 Feb 2024 08:38:39 +0100</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://geco-group.org/media/logo_hue21406914225b119becd577af1fb7f4d_583632_300x300_fit_lanczos_3.png</url>
      <title>FLUXNET</title>
      <link>https://geco-group.org/tag/fluxnet/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Master thesis - Global land carbon cycle modelling</title>
      <link>https://geco-group.org/joinus/global_biomee/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 Feb 2024 08:38:39 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://geco-group.org/joinus/global_biomee/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;background&#34;&gt;Background&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dynamic Global Vegetation Models (DGVMs) are key tools for understanding biosphere-climate feedbacks and transient vegetation dynamics in response to global change. A novel vegetation demography model, the BiomeE, is a mechanistic cohort-based model which simulates vegetation dynamics and biogeochemical processes. This mechanistic model is able to simulate the size dependent competition, and thereby links plant functional traits, physiology, forest demography and stand dynamics. The GECO group has developed of a new framework for modelling of terrestrial biosphere processes (&lt;a href=&#34;https://geco-bern.github.io/rsofun/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;rsofun&lt;/a&gt;) that combines the BiomeE model with a photosynthesis model using optimality principles (P-model). This framework has been used to run site-level simulations in different regions, including boreal, temperate and tropical forests. Still, a global simulation capturing global patterns, has not carried out yet, but will be the basis for our future research on the global carbon cycle, potentially leading to participation in simulation activities for the Global Carbon Project. This thesis is an ideal entry point for your work in this direction.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /media/global_biomee_hu1fc26a5764c71c7ad2dd83d1c5d21ac2_1475022_0bb60b5e0ba5bc3736229262bfa4750c.webp 400w,
               /media/global_biomee_hu1fc26a5764c71c7ad2dd83d1c5d21ac2_1475022_f30e2bdc15bb137e41da1b24a5282103.webp 760w,
               /media/global_biomee_hu1fc26a5764c71c7ad2dd83d1c5d21ac2_1475022_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos_3.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://geco-group.org/media/global_biomee_hu1fc26a5764c71c7ad2dd83d1c5d21ac2_1475022_0bb60b5e0ba5bc3736229262bfa4750c.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;760&#34;
               height=&#34;288&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Above: Prescribed global distribution of plant functional types. Figure from &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.5194/gmd-15-8153-2022&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Weng et al., 2022&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;aim&#34;&gt;Aim&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Develop a wrapper for pixel-wise (parallelised) rsofun calls, given a path to global forcing files, as an R package.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Run BiomeE with P-model.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Preparations for Global Carbon Project simulations&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;requirements&#34;&gt;Requirements&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The student is motivated to work and contribute to the development of a new modelling framework.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Experience working with R or other data science tools are a prerequisite.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Basic understanding of mathematical modelling and a keen interest to delve deeper into modelling and programming (R)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The student writes the thesis in English.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;literature&#34;&gt;Literature&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Weng, E. S., Malyshev, S., Lichstein, J. W., Farrior, C. E., Dybzinski, R., Zhang, T., Shevliakova, E., and Pacala, S. W. 2015: Scaling from individual trees to forests in an Earth system modeling framework using a mathematically tractable model of height-structured competition, Biogeosciences, 12, 2655–2694, &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.5194/bg-12-2655-2015&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://doi.org/10.5194/bg-12-2655-2015&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Weng, E., Dybzinski, R., Farrior, C. E., and Pacala, S. W. 2019: Competition alters predicted forest carbon cycle responses to nitrogen availability and elevated CO2: simulations using an explicitly competitive, game-theoretic vegetation demographic model, Biogeosciences, 16, 4577–4599, &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.5194/bg-16-4577-2019&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://doi.org/10.5194/bg-16-4577-2019&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Stocker, B. D., Wang, H., Smith, N. G., Harrison, S. P., Keenan, T. F., Sandoval, D., Davis, T., and Prentice, I. C. 2020: P-model v1.0: an optimality-based light use efficiency model for simulating ecosystem gross primary production, Geosci. Model Dev., 13, 1545–1581, &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.5194/gmd-13-1545-2020&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://doi.org/10.5194/gmd-13-1545-2020&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Weng, E., Aleinov, I., Singh, R., Puma, M. J., McDermid, S. S., Kiang, N. Y., Kelley, M., Wilcox, K., Dybzinski, R., Farrior, C. E., Pacala, S. W., and Cook, B. I. 2022: Modeling demographic-driven vegetation dynamics and ecosystem biogeochemical cycling in NASA GISS&amp;rsquo;s Earth system model (ModelE-BiomeE v.1.0), Geosci. Model Dev., 15, 8153–8180, &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.5194/gmd-15-8153-2022&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://doi.org/10.5194/gmd-15-8153-2022&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;supervision&#34;&gt;Supervision&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Dr. Laura Marqués&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Prof. Benjamin Stocker&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Bachelor thesis - Importance of GPP extremes in eddy covariance data</title>
      <link>https://geco-group.org/joinus/gpp_extremes/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 Feb 2024 08:32:52 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://geco-group.org/joinus/gpp_extremes/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;background&#34;&gt;Background&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The gross primary production (GPP) of an ecosystem, that is, the carbon it assimilates via photosynthesis, differs strongly from one year to the next. This variability between years is called the interannual variability (IAV) of GPP and the reasons for why GPP can change substantially from year to year are unclear. From a global scale analysis, we know that the seasonal cycles in precipitation and temperature in semi-arid ecoystems contribute substantially to the global IAV of GPP, highlighting the role of water and heat. We also know that even a few unusual hours in a total year can contribute disproportionately more to an ecosystems annual carbon uptake. For example, just 2% of unusually hot hours can account for ca. 10% of an ecosystems’ total annual GPP. Considering an increase in frequency and intensity of extreme events under climate change, a better quantification and characterisation of GPP extremes is crucial to estimate the future global carbon balance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;aim&#34;&gt;Aim&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The goal of this project is to quantify the role of GPP extremes on an ecosystem’s carbon uptake, using FLUXNET data (half-hourly measured land-atmosphere exchange of carbon dioxide). The first aim is to identify years that show GPP extremes, that is, anomalies in their annual total GPP. Then, a suitable method to assess the effect of extreme days within these anomalous years on the year’s total GPP is explored by (e.g., using a Gini index). Further questions may cover investigating the difference across globally distributed sites or comparing observed against modelled GPP to identify the drivers of GPP extremes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;requirements&#34;&gt;Requirements&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Most important: High motivation to work on questions related to land-atmosphere exchange and the carbon cycle - everything else can be learned!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Confidence to work with large datasets of the terrestrial biosphere.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Experience working with R or other data science tools are an advantage.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The student writes the thesis in English.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;literature&#34;&gt;Literature&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ahlström A, Raupach MR, Schurgers G, Smith B, Arneth A, Jung M, Reichstein M, Canadell JG, Friedlingstein P, Jain AK, &lt;em&gt;et al.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;strong&gt;2015&lt;/strong&gt;. The dominant role of semi-arid ecosystems in the trend and variability of the land CO 2 sink. &lt;em&gt;Science&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;348&lt;/strong&gt;: 895–899.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Kannenberg SA, Bowling DR, Anderegg WRL&lt;/strong&gt;. &lt;strong&gt;2020&lt;/strong&gt;. Hot moments in ecosystem fluxes: High GPP anomalies exert outsized influence on the carbon cycle and are differentially driven by moisture availability across biomes. &lt;em&gt;Environmental Research Letters&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;15&lt;/strong&gt;: 054004.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Launiainen S, Katul GG, Leppä K, Kolari P, Aslan T, Grönholm T, Korhonen L, Mammarella I, Vesala T&lt;/strong&gt;. &lt;strong&gt;2022&lt;/strong&gt;. Does growing atmospheric CO 2 explain increasing carbon sink in a boreal coniferous forest? &lt;em&gt;Global Change Biology&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;28&lt;/strong&gt;: 2910–2929.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Wieder WR, Butterfield Z, Lindsay K, Lombardozzi DL, Keppel‐Aleks G&lt;/strong&gt;. &lt;strong&gt;2021&lt;/strong&gt;. Interannual and Seasonal Drivers of Carbon Cycle Variability Represented by the Community Earth System Model (CESM2). &lt;em&gt;Global Biogeochemical Cycles&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;35&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;supervision&#34;&gt;Supervision&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Prof. Benjamin Stocker&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Bachelor or Master thesis - Indentifying frost events and impacts in ecosystem flux measurements</title>
      <link>https://geco-group.org/joinus/frost_gpp/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 Feb 2024 08:24:51 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://geco-group.org/joinus/frost_gpp/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Supervision:&lt;/strong&gt; Prof. Benjamin Stocker, &lt;strong&gt;Co-supervision:&lt;/strong&gt; Dr. Laura Marqués, Dr. Yann Vitasse (WSL Birmensdorf)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;background&#34;&gt;Background&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Climate warming is driving an advance of leaf unfolding in trees, promoting longer growing seasons. However, the advance of the start-of-the-season (SOS) can induce &lt;em&gt;false springs&lt;/em&gt;, i.e., a stretch of unexpectedly warmer temperatures in late winter/early spring followed by sudden freezing events. These frost events after the SOS can affect the structure and function of terrestrial ecosystems and have important environmental and economic consequences. Still, there is little consensus on how frost events change under global warming and the implications. Therefore, it is relevant to understand the occurrence of frost events once the growing season has started and how they change among regions in temperate and boreal forests.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;aim&#34;&gt;Aim&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The goal of this project is to identify when the frost events happen after the SOS and quantify their impact on carbon fluxes. The student will characterize the SOS using phenological measurements and ecosystem-level photosynthesis (gross primary production, GPP). Daily minimum temperatures will be used to calculate the number of frost events. The project design includes combining ground observations, eddy covariance flux measurements, remote sensing data and global climate datasets.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If addressed as a MSc topic, there is a possiblity for a publication as a thesis outcome.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;requirements&#34;&gt;Requirements&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The student is motivated to work with large datasets of the terrestrial biosphere.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Experience working with R or other data science tools are an advantage.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The student writes the thesis in English.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;literature&#34;&gt;Literature&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Chamberlain,  C.J., Cook, B.I., Morales-Castilla, I. and Wolkovich, E.M. (2021).  Climate change reshapes the drivers of false spring risk across European trees. New Phytol, 229: 323-334.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Liu,  Q., Piao, S., Janssens, I.A. et al. (2018). Extension of the growing season increases vegetation exposure to frost. Nat Commun 9, 426 .&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Hufkens,  K., Friedl, M.A., Keenan, T.F., Sonnentag, O., Bailey, A., O&amp;rsquo;Keefe, J. and Richardson, A.D. (2012). Ecological impacts of a widespread frost event following early spring leaf-out. Glob Change Biol, 18: 2365-2377.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Piao, S, Liu, Q, Chen, A, et al. (2019). Plant phenology and global climate change: Current progresses and challenges. Glob Change Biol. 25: 1922– 1940.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Bachelor thesis - Ecosystem water balance and subsurface hydrology</title>
      <link>https://geco-group.org/joinus/ecosystem_waterbalance/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 Feb 2024 08:24:51 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://geco-group.org/joinus/ecosystem_waterbalance/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Supervision:&lt;/strong&gt; Prof. Benjamin Stocker&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;background&#34;&gt;Background&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Exchange fluxes of water vapour between ecosystems and the atmosphere are commonly measured using eddy-covariance technique. This gives information about how much water is transpired by plants and evaporated from soil and plant surfaces. Such fluxes are measured across a hundreds of sites globally, data is available and regularly used in our group, and interesting patterns emerge. For example, some sites appear to evaporate a large fraction of annual precipitation. Some even more than annual precipitation. This raises important questions: Is this a data artefact? Or are there topographic and hydrological patterns that can explain differences between sites?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;aim&#34;&gt;Aim&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This thesis will perform data analyses to relate measured annual mean evapotranspiration to site characteristics. Additional data will be prepared for characterising sites in terms of hydrological, topographic, soil, vegetation, and other aspects. The hypothesis to be tested is that sites that exhibit a high ratio of mean annual evapotranspiration over precipitation are located in topographic depressions, where subsurface water flow supplies water for evapotranspiration.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;requirements&#34;&gt;Requirements&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The student is motivated to work with large datasets of the terrestrial biosphere.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Experience working with R or other data science tools are an advantage.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The student writes the thesis in English.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;literature&#34;&gt;Literature&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://geco-bern.github.io/les/ecohydrology.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Land in the Earth System Chapter Ecohydrology&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Williams, C. A., Reichstein, M., Buchmann, N., Baldocchi, D., Beer, C., Schwalm, C., Wohlfahrt, G., Hasler, N., Bernhofer, C., Foken, T., Papale, D., Schymanski, S., and Schaefer, K.: Climate and vegetation controls on the surface water balance: Synthesis of evapotranspiration measured across a global network of flux towers, Water Resources Research, 48, &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1029/2011WR011586&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://doi.org/10.1029/2011WR011586&lt;/a&gt;, 2012.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Thompson, S. E., Harman, C. J., Konings, A. G., Sivapalan, M., Neal, A., and Troch, P. A.: Comparative hydrology across AmeriFlux sites: The variable roles of climate, vegetation, and groundwater, Water Resources Research, 47, &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1029/2010WR009797&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://doi.org/10.1029/2010WR009797&lt;/a&gt;, 2011.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>An effective machine learning approach for predicting ecosystem CO$_textrm2$ assimilation across space and time</title>
      <link>https://geco-group.org/publication/debartolomeis-23-egu/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Sep 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://geco-group.org/publication/debartolomeis-23-egu/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Bachelor thesis - Soil texture for ET modelling</title>
      <link>https://geco-group.org/joinus_old/soiltext_et/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 21 Feb 2023 10:50:18 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://geco-group.org/joinus_old/soiltext_et/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;background&#34;&gt;Background&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Global terrestrial gross primary production (GPP), i.e., the uptake of CO2 by terrestrial plants, is often limited by the availability of soil water for evapotranspiration (ET). The amount of water a plant can take up from the soil depends on the soil texture, the depth of plant roots, and the storage capacity of the soil in the plant’s rooting zone. While long-term measurements of GPP and ET are available from sites across the globe (called the FLUXNET network), soil texture properties are not available in a common database. This project aims to assemble a datset of soil properties and plant traits at FLUXNET sites, and use it to predict ET over daily and weekly timescales.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;aim&#34;&gt;Aim&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The goals of this project are as follows:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Assemble data on soil properties and traits at FLUXNET sites&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Calibrate an existing water balance model based on its predictions of top-soil moisture content&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Predict ET and cumulative water deficits and validate the same with flux data&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;requirements&#34;&gt;Requirements&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Most important: High motivation to work on questions related to land-atmosphere exchange and the carbon cycle - everything else can be learned!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Interest in working with large datasets of the terrestrial biosphere.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Experience working with R or other data science tools are an advantage.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The student writes the thesis in English.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;literature&#34;&gt;Literature&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Stocker, B.D., Tumber-Dávila, S.J., Konings, A.G. &lt;em&gt;et al.&lt;/em&gt;  Global patterns of water storage in the rooting zones of vegetation. &lt;em&gt;Nat. Geosci.&lt;/em&gt;  (2023). &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1038/s41561-023-01125-2&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://doi.org/10.1038/s41561-023-01125-2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;supervision&#34;&gt;Supervision&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Prof. Benjamin Stocke&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Dr. Jaideep Joshi&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Acclimation of phenology relieves leaf longevity constraints in deciduous forests</title>
      <link>https://geco-group.org/publication/marques-23-natee/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Jan 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://geco-group.org/publication/marques-23-natee/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Environmental controls on the light use efficiency of terrestrial gross primary production</title>
      <link>https://geco-group.org/publication/bloomfield-22-gcb/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://geco-group.org/publication/bloomfield-22-gcb/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
