<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Joinus_olds | Geocomputation and Earth Observation</title>
    <link>https://geco-group.org/joinus_old/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://geco-group.org/joinus_old/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Joinus_olds</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Fri, 05 Apr 2024 08:57:24 +0100</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://geco-group.org/media/logo_hue21406914225b119becd577af1fb7f4d_583632_300x300_fit_lanczos_3.png</url>
      <title>Joinus_olds</title>
      <link>https://geco-group.org/joinus_old/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>PhD in Climate Sciences: Next-generation vegetation modelling (100%)</title>
      <link>https://geco-group.org/joinus_old/phd_lemontree/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Apr 2024 08:57:24 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://geco-group.org/joinus_old/phd_lemontree/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Institute of Geography and Oeschger Centre for Climate Change Research, University of Bern&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Start of employment: 01.09.2024 (latest)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Temporary employment&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Our group&lt;/strong&gt; for Geocomputation and Earth Observation develops new model and data integration methods to gain a mechanistic understanding of biogeochemical cycling in ecosystems, water-carbon coupling, and forest responses to climate change. We are hosted at the Institute of Geography, University of Bern, and work at the intersection of Earth system science, ecophysiology, ecology, applied statistics, and high-performance computing. Within the Virtual Earth Systems Research Insitute project LEMONTREE (Land Ecosystem Models based On New Theory, obseRvations, and ExperimEnts), we are recruiting a PhD student.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Background&lt;/strong&gt;  This project will tackle one of the major sources for uncertainty in climate and Earth system projections reliable predictions of how water and nutrients govern vegetation, carbon and water cycling, and their responses to a changing climate and CO2. The aim is to integrate eco-evolutionary optimality theory and observational constraints into a dynamic model for simulating global land ecosystem functioning and structure.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Tasks&lt;/strong&gt;  You will innovate towards a next-generation vegetation model by combining improved ecosystem process understanding and first principles, numerical modelling, and model-data integration methods. Your work will extend the model developed and maintained in our group, integrating novel theory development by the LEMONTREE project partners. You will apply the model for testing novel theory against different observational data, including satellite remote sensing observations, ecosystem flux data, and ecosystem manipulation experiments. The PhD will be designed to maintaining intellectual freedom to refine project directions. Your work will generate improved predictive methods for climate change impacts in land ecosystems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Requirements&lt;/strong&gt;  The candidate must hold a MSc degree in natural sciences, mathematics, or engineering and should demonstrate proficient English written and oral skills and excellent analytical and numerical skills. Experience with programming and other data science methods are an asset and an open and collaborative mentality for the development of our computational infrastructure is expected. The latest starting date for the PhD project is September 2024.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;We offer&lt;/strong&gt; the candidate to be part of a small group with a strong collaborative philosophy and to benefit from a leading academic environment, from an international collaboration within the project and from the excellent quality of life in Switzerland. This PhD will be placed within the Graduate School of Climate Sciences at Oeschger Centre for Climate Change Research (OCCR) and will draw on supervisory expertise and that bridges ecosystem science, hydrology, vegetation modelling, and climate science.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;For further information&lt;/strong&gt; about our group please visit Geco-group.org. Questions regarding the position should be directed to Prof. B. Stocker by email: &lt;a href=&#34;mailto:benjamin.stocker@unibe.ch&#34;&gt;benjamin.stocker@unibe.ch&lt;/a&gt; (no applications).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Interested?&lt;/strong&gt;  We look forward to receiving your online application including the following documents: Motivation letter (max. 2 pages, with a statement of research interests), a CV, copies of academic qualifications and the names and e-mail addresses of three referees. Please submit your application before 31 May 2024 to &lt;a href=&#34;mailto:geco.bern@gmail.com&#34;&gt;geco.bern@gmail.com&lt;/a&gt; with the subject &amp;lsquo;geco-002&amp;rsquo;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Postdoc in drone-based vegetation water stress monitoring</title>
      <link>https://geco-group.org/joinus_old/postdoc_uav/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 May 2023 08:46:40 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://geco-group.org/joinus_old/postdoc_uav/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Our group for Geocomputation and Earth Observation develops new model and data integration methods to gain a mechanistic understanding of the terrestrial biosphere. We are hosted at the Geography Institute of the University of Bern and work at the intersection of Earth system science, remote sensing, ecology, and hydrology.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This position serves to establish and consolidate near-range remote sensing capacities in our research group and integrate field-based research within the context of our research on drought impact monitoring and prediction.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;tasks&#34;&gt;Tasks&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You will plan and perform a drone-based surface reflectance remote sensing campaign for water stress detection in Swiss forests. You will analyse data and lead publications on vegetation water stress relations across landscape-scale gradients.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;requirements&#34;&gt;Requirements&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The candidate must hold a Ph.D. degree in a relevant field. Experience in drone-based remote sensing with completed training in the operation of UAVs, ideally with license, experience in managing field campaigns, and experience with close-range remote sensing data post-processing are required. The candidate should demonstrate proficient English written and oral skills. We expect a collaborative mentality and enthusiasm for the development of our computational infrastructure and open-source software.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;we-offer&#34;&gt;We offer&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We offer the candidate to be part of a growing group with a strong collaborative philosophy and and a tight international network of leading partners, providing further career development opportunities toward future academic or industry positions. You will benefit from a supporting academic environment and from the attractive quality of life in Switzerland.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We look forward to receiving your online application including the following documents: Motivation letter (max. 2 pages, with a statement of research interests and demonstrated experience with software development projects), a CV, copies of academic qualifications and the names and e-mail addresses of three referees. Please note that we exclusively accept applications submitted through our online application portal. Applications via email or postal services will not be considered. We continue recruitment until a suitable candidate is found. The start of this position is at your earliest convenience. The position is offered for one year with possibility for continuation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Questions regarding the position should be directed to Dr. Koen Hufkens (&lt;a href=&#34;mailto:koen.hufkens@giub.unibe.ch&#34;&gt;koen.hufkens@giub.unibe.ch&lt;/a&gt;) (no applications). You can apply for this position by following &lt;a href=&#34;https://ohws.prospective.ch/public/v1/redirect/ebd3c469-7556-435a-9857-c9a4e8f717eb/ats/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;THIS LINK&lt;/a&gt; to the online submission platform.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Bachelor thesis - Soil texture for ET modelling</title>
      <link>https://geco-group.org/joinus_old/soiltext_et/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 21 Feb 2023 10:50:18 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://geco-group.org/joinus_old/soiltext_et/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;background&#34;&gt;Background&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Global terrestrial gross primary production (GPP), i.e., the uptake of CO2 by terrestrial plants, is often limited by the availability of soil water for evapotranspiration (ET). The amount of water a plant can take up from the soil depends on the soil texture, the depth of plant roots, and the storage capacity of the soil in the plant’s rooting zone. While long-term measurements of GPP and ET are available from sites across the globe (called the FLUXNET network), soil texture properties are not available in a common database. This project aims to assemble a datset of soil properties and plant traits at FLUXNET sites, and use it to predict ET over daily and weekly timescales.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;aim&#34;&gt;Aim&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The goals of this project are as follows:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Assemble data on soil properties and traits at FLUXNET sites&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Calibrate an existing water balance model based on its predictions of top-soil moisture content&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Predict ET and cumulative water deficits and validate the same with flux data&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;requirements&#34;&gt;Requirements&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Most important: High motivation to work on questions related to land-atmosphere exchange and the carbon cycle - everything else can be learned!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Interest in working with large datasets of the terrestrial biosphere.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Experience working with R or other data science tools are an advantage.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The student writes the thesis in English.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;literature&#34;&gt;Literature&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Stocker, B.D., Tumber-Dávila, S.J., Konings, A.G. &lt;em&gt;et al.&lt;/em&gt;  Global patterns of water storage in the rooting zones of vegetation. &lt;em&gt;Nat. Geosci.&lt;/em&gt;  (2023). &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1038/s41561-023-01125-2&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://doi.org/10.1038/s41561-023-01125-2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;supervision&#34;&gt;Supervision&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Prof. Benjamin Stocke&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Dr. Jaideep Joshi&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Master thesis - Modelling optimal acclimation across canopy gradients</title>
      <link>https://geco-group.org/joinus_old/canopy_gradients/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 21 Feb 2023 09:09:34 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://geco-group.org/joinus_old/canopy_gradients/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;background&#34;&gt;Background&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The rate of CO2 uptake by photosynthesis is determined by the acclimation of leaves to the prevailing light environment. In dense forests, light intensity decreases exponentially as we go from the top of the canopy towards the ground, as light is absorbed and scattered by leaves. However, the acclimated photosynthetic capacity of understorey leaves is higher than what we would expect based on the exponential decay of light. This is because these leaves acclimate to sun-flecks - small flecks of sunlight appear in understory due to gaps in the canopy, and because of the movement of the sun through the sky. Therefore, predicting the acclimation of understorey leaves requires considering the variability in light availability.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;aim&#34;&gt;Aim&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The goals of this project are:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To quantify the variability in direct and diffuse sunlight in the understorey, either using either a radiative transfer model, or using fat-tailed probability distributions&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To use the P-model of photosynthesis to predict the optimal acclimation of photosynthetic capacity given the distribution of light intensity&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To test the model predictions with data on canopy gradients from the CH-Lae site and possibly from the Netravali site.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;requirements&#34;&gt;Requirements&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Most important: High motivation to work on questions related to plant physiology.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Basic understanding of mathematical modelling and a keen interest to delve deeper into modelling and programming (R, Fortran)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Experience working with R or other data science tools are a prerequisite.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The student writes the thesis in English.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;methods&#34;&gt;Methods&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Implement the P-model (or some concept of optimality) in SPA (or any other model that simulates light gradient in canopy) at different levels of canopy depth and predict within-canopy gradients in photosynthetic capacity, leaf N, and LMA.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;supervision&#34;&gt;Supervision&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Jaideep Joshi&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Pascal Schneider&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Prof. Benjamin Stocker&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Master thesis - Global evapotranspiration modelling</title>
      <link>https://geco-group.org/joinus_old/global_et/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 21 Feb 2023 08:40:38 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://geco-group.org/joinus_old/global_et/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;background&#34;&gt;Background&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Global terrestrial gross primary production (GPP), i.e., the uptake of CO2 by terrestrial plants, is often limited by the availability of soil water. The amount of water a plant can take up from the soil depends on the soil texture, the depth of plant roots, and the storage capacity of the soil in the plant’s rooting zone. Global vegetation models typically only consider moisture content in the top 2m of soil, which is often not representative of the moisture conditions actually experienced by plants. In recent research, a more accurate global map of root-zone water storage capacity has been developed. This project aims at predicting and analyzing the properties of global evapo-transpiration (ET) based on this new map.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;aim&#34;&gt;Aim&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The goals of this project are as follows:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Extend a soil water balance model being developed in Prof. Stocker’s group to predict ET based on root-zone water storage capacity (RZWC)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Drive the model at a global scale using a recently-developed map of RZWC&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Analyze the interannual/intraannual variability in ET, test model predictions against the Budyko relationship, and test memory effects (due to water storage) on ET.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;requirements&#34;&gt;Requirements&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Most important: High motivation to work on questions related to land-atmosphere exchange and the carbon cycle - everything else can be learned!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Confidence to work with large datasets of the terrestrial biosphere.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Experience working with R or other data science tools are a prerequisite.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Basic understanding of mathematical modelling and a keen interest to delve deeper into modelling and programming (R and Fortran)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The student writes the thesis in English.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;literature&#34;&gt;Literature&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Stocker, B.D., Tumber-Dávila, S.J., Konings, A.G. &lt;em&gt;et al.&lt;/em&gt;  Global patterns of water storage in the rooting zones of vegetation. &lt;em&gt;Nat. Geosci.&lt;/em&gt;  (2023). &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1038/s41561-023-01125-2&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://doi.org/10.1038/s41561-023-01125-2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Master thesis - Droughts in the last millennium</title>
      <link>https://geco-group.org/joinus_old/cwd_millennium/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 21 Feb 2023 08:36:01 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://geco-group.org/joinus_old/cwd_millennium/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;background&#34;&gt;Background&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is a current scientific debate if the intensity of the recent 2003, 2015, and 2018 droughts is exceptional in the context of the last millennium. Based on tree-ring reconstructions, some authors find them to be within the range of natural variability (Ionita et al. 2021), while others describe them to be unprecedented (Büntgen et al. 2021). Our new climate reconstructions, generated by data-informed climate model simulations enable a testing of these hypotheses (Hand et al., 2023).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;aim&#34;&gt;Aim&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The goal of this thesis is the analysis of droughts in our new climate reconstruction, which combines various kinds of direct and indirect observations with model simulations since 1420 CE. The drought magnitude will be quantified by considering cumulative water deficits and the long-term statistics of drought event magnitudes will be established. The climate reconstruction (from observations-informed climate model simulations) would allow to study also possible causes like Atlantic sea surface temperature variability or shifts in large-scale atmospheric circulation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;requirements&#34;&gt;Requirements&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Interest in working with large datasets from climate model outputs.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Experience working with R or other data science tools are an advantage.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The student writes the thesis in English.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;supervision&#34;&gt;Supervision&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Prof. Benjamin Stocker, Prof. Stefan Brönnimann&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;references&#34;&gt;References&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Hand, R., Samakinwa, E., Lipfert, L., and Brönnimann, S.: ModE-Sim – a medium-sized atmospheric general circulation model (AGCM) ensemble to study climate variability during the modern era (1420 to 2009), Geoscientific Model Development, 16, 4853–4866, &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.5194/gmd-16-4853-2023&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://doi.org/10.5194/gmd-16-4853-2023&lt;/a&gt;, 2023.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Ionita, M., Dima, M., Nagavciuc, V. et al. Past megadroughts in central Europe were longer, more severe and less warm than modern droughts. Commun Earth Environ 2, 61 (2021). &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1038/s43247-021-00130-w&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://doi.org/10.1038/s43247-021-00130-w&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Büntgen, U., Urban, O., Krusic, P.J. et al. Recent European drought extremes beyond Common Era background variability. Nat. Geosci. 14, 190–196 (2021). &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1038/s41561-021-00698-0&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://doi.org/10.1038/s41561-021-00698-0&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Master thesis - Global ecosystem flux modelling</title>
      <link>https://geco-group.org/joinus_old/eeo_fluxes/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Mar 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://geco-group.org/joinus_old/eeo_fluxes/</guid>
      <description>&lt;!-- 

&lt;div class=&#34;alert alert-note&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div&gt;
    Click on the &lt;strong&gt;Slides&lt;/strong&gt; button above to view the built-in slides feature.
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
 --&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Main supervision:&lt;/strong&gt; Prof. Dr. Benjamin Stocker
&lt;strong&gt;Co-supervision:&lt;/strong&gt; Francesco Giardina&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a result of the higher CO2 concentration in the atmosphere, plants have adapted their stomatal regulation to increase the water-use efficiency (WUE) at the leaf level. Another driver of plant transpiration is foliage surface area, and trends in land surface greenness are thus partly linked by enhanced WUE under elevated CO2. As climate change progresses, it is critical to understand the responses of terrestrial ecosystems and surface-atmosphere exchanges of CO2 and water vapour to global environmental change.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The objective of this project is to model spatial and seasonal variations in WUE to predict evapotranspiration (ET) within an established global photosynthesis and acclimation model (productivity model or simply P-model; Stocker et al. 2020). The core of this model employs a principle of eco-evolutionary optimality to simulate acclimation of photosynthesis and transpiration based on the trade-off between costs and benefits from water loss and C assimilation. You will use observed root zone moisture storage capacity (SR) to model ET at FLUXNET sites and investigate predictions under progressing droughts. We expect that using the combination of the two key quantities WUE and SR, which are under plant-control and subject to different acclimation and adaptation across the Earth?s climate zones, will improve global ET predictions. It has been demonstrated that rooting zone adapts its extent as a function of the phase lag between peak seasonal radiation and precipitation. Following this framework, we will investigate the effect of a spatially varying rooting depth on the ratio of actual ET over precipitation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This thesis is a great starting point for mechanistic ecosystem modelling and working with large datasets of the terrestrial biosphere. Basic experience with working with R, Python, Fortran, or other programming languages are a requirement. You may start as soon as you like. Please contact me directly if you&amp;rsquo;re interested.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is possible to carry out this thesis in teamwork, where the partner thesis would implement a predictive model based on machine-learning instead of a mechanistic model.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Master thesis - Preindustrial land use change</title>
      <link>https://geco-group.org/joinus_old/landcover6k/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Mar 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://geco-group.org/joinus_old/landcover6k/</guid>
      <description>&lt;!-- 

&lt;div class=&#34;alert alert-note&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div&gt;
    Click on the &lt;strong&gt;Slides&lt;/strong&gt; button above to view the built-in slides feature.
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
 --&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Main supervision:&lt;/strong&gt; Prof. Dr. Benjamin Stocker
&lt;strong&gt;Co-supervision:&lt;/strong&gt; Prof. Dr. Fortunat Joos, Climate and Environmental Physics, Universität Bern&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Human land use and land use change (LULUC) has transformed the Earth surface and is contributing to the rise in atmospheric greenhouse gas concentrations and climate change. In contrast to fossil fuel combustion, LULUC has potentially been an agent of Earth system transformation already before the Industrial period. Indeed, several prominent features in ice core records of the past 10,000 years have been linked to the rise and collapse of civilizations. However, establishing causal links and understanding the role of pre-industrial human societies in the Earth system has been challenging. Emerging past LULUC reconstructions combine insights from multiple disciplines (Archaeology, Earth system science, Land use Science and Geography) and provide a new basis for simulating impacts with Earth System Models. This is where you step in.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You will use the latest reconstructions of Holocene LULUC from the PAGES Landcover6K working group (&lt;a href=&#34;http://pastglobalchanges.org/science/wg/landcover6k/intro&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;http://pastglobalchanges.org/science/wg/landcover6k/intro,&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://stineb.github.io/holoLU_lc6k/index.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://stineb.github.io/holoLU_lc6k/index.html&lt;/a&gt;) to run a set of global model simulations for evaluating impacts of pre-industrial LULUC on the terrestrial carbon balance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This thesis is a great starting point for working with global Earth system and vegetation models and large spatial datasets, and for linking disciplines. Experience with programming is an advantage and your eagerness to learn a prerequisite. You may start as soon as you like.
&lt;a href=&#34;https://stineb.github.io/holoLU_lc6k/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://stineb.github.io/holoLU_lc6k/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
