<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Pascal Schneider | Geocomputation and Earth Observation</title>
    <link>https://geco-group.org/author/pascal-schneider/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://geco-group.org/author/pascal-schneider/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Pascal Schneider</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Wed, 13 Sep 2023 23:06:27 +0200</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://geco-group.org/author/pascal-schneider/avatar_hu90b50fac7222b9fc2af4d504f83ab02c_488611_270x270_fill_q75_lanczos_center.jpg</url>
      <title>Pascal Schneider</title>
      <link>https://geco-group.org/author/pascal-schneider/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Leaf Temperature&#39;s Role in Ecosystem Modeling</title>
      <link>https://geco-group.org/post/leaf-temperature-tutorial/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 13 Sep 2023 23:06:27 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>https://geco-group.org/post/leaf-temperature-tutorial/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In the realm of ecological research, leaf temperature has emerged as a quietly significant player. While seemingly inconspicuous, it holds the key to understanding the inner workings of an ecosystem&amp;rsquo;s carbon and water cycle and the processes that drive them. Imagine climate scientists striving for precision in their vegetation models or aiming to decipher intricate ecological relationships. Leaf temperature is the critical piece of this puzzle.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The debate surrounding leaf thermoregulation, the question of how leaves manage their temperature, has sparked a considerable discussions. Can plants actively control their leaf temperature? If so, when and how? This debate remains unsettled, with compelling arguments on both sides.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Adding to this intrigue is the application of eco-evolutionary optimality theory (EEO). EEO leverages natural selection&amp;rsquo;s power to shape vegetation patterns based on climate. It suggests that ecosystem traits are outcomes of climate-driven evolution. By applying EEO principles, we can predict essential photosynthetic processes solely from environmental data, revolutionizing Earth system models. And so, they might also provide important insights in thermoregulation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But the story doesn&amp;rsquo;t end there. The quest to decipher leaf temperature continues with diverse data sources and methods, uniting ecologists, data scientists, and climate experts. This interdisciplinary endeavor makes leaf temperature a captivating field to explore.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you&amp;rsquo;re captivated by this riddle of leaf temperature and its profound implications for our understanding of ecosystems, delve deeper into this subject through our online &lt;a href=&#34;https://padasch.github.io/leaf_energy_balance_tutorial/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;tutorial&lt;/a&gt;. Discover the ongoing debate, evolving theories, and the potential EEO holds for more precise Earth system modeling. Leaf temperature may seem unassuming, but its significance in ecology and predicting our Earth&amp;rsquo;s future is undeniable. Join us in unlocking its secrets!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>GECO at EGU 2023</title>
      <link>https://geco-group.org/post/geco_at_egu2023/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Apr 2023 16:46:36 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>https://geco-group.org/post/geco_at_egu2023/</guid>
      <description>&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our group is contributing to this year&amp;rsquo;s EGU General Assembly with various sessions, talks, and posters! See below for when and where you can find us.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;sessions&#34;&gt;Sessions&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Thursday (27 April)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://meetingorganizer.copernicus.org/EGU23/session/44989&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;BG3.15:&lt;/strong&gt; Terrestrial ecosystem responses to global change: integrating experiments, ecosystem observations, and models to understand carbon, nutrient, and water cycling&lt;/a&gt; convened by Benjamin D. Stocker
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Orals: Wed, 26 Apr, 08:30–10:00 (CEST), 10:45–12:25 (CEST), Room C&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Poster Attendance: Fri, 28 Apr, 14:00–15:45 (CEST), Hall A&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;talks&#34;&gt;Talks&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Monday (24 April)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://meetingorganizer.copernicus.org/EGU23/EGU23-12108.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Photosynthesis acclimates to warming through predictable changes in photosynthetic capacities, stomatal sensitivity and enzyme kinetics&lt;/a&gt; by Pascal D. Schneider (Mon, 24 Apr, 15:15–15:25, Room 2.95)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Tuesday (25 April)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://meetingorganizer.copernicus.org/EGU23/EGU23-9503.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Towards a better understanding of deep belowground water stores and their influence on land-atmosphere exchange and drought impacts&lt;/a&gt; by Benjamin D. Stocker (Tue, 25 Apr, 10:50–11:10, Room 3.16/17)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Wednesday (26 April)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://meetingorganizer.copernicus.org/EGU23/EGU23-10303.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Divergent phenology response to nitrogen addition between a Mediterranean and a boreal forest&lt;/a&gt; by Yunpeng Luo (Wed, 26 Apr, 10:55–11:05, Room C)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Thursday (27 April)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://meetingorganizer.copernicus.org/EGU23/EGU23-9374.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Ecosystem C and N cycle interactions – diverse model representations and divergent model predictions versus collective empirical constraints&lt;/a&gt; by Benjamin D. Stocker (Thu, 27 Apr, 08:35–08:45, Room N2)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://meetingorganizer.copernicus.org/EGU23/EGU23-9757.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Roles of diversity and adaptation in the eco-evolutionary responses of biodiverse plant communities to climate change&lt;/a&gt; by Jaideep Joshi (Thu, 27 Apr, 09:05–09:15, Room N2)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://meetingorganizer.copernicus.org/EGU23/EGU23-12437.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Forest Drought Impact Prediction based on Spatio-temporal Satellite Imagery and Weather Forecasts &amp;ndash; A Spatio-Temporal Approach using Convolutional LSTM Models&lt;/a&gt; by Emine Didem Durukan (Thu, 27 Apr, 11:20–11:30, Room B)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://meetingorganizer.copernicus.org/EGU23/EGU23-12672.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Forest drought impact prediction based on satellite imagery and weather forecasts - a spatially distributed approach using a recurrent deep neural network&lt;/a&gt; by Sélène Ledain (Thu, 27 Apr, 11:30–11:40, Room B)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;posters&#34;&gt;Posters&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://meetingorganizer.copernicus.org/EGU23/EGU23-3984.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Global environmental controls of land nitrous oxide emissions inferred from field and experimental measurements&lt;/a&gt; by Yunke Peng (Attendance: Fri, 28 Apr, 08:30–10:15, Hall A, A.260)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


















&lt;figure  id=&#34;figure-qr-code-to-this-blog-post&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://geco-group.org/post/geco_at_egu2023/&#34;  target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;QR-Code to this blog post.&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /post/geco_at_egu2023/qr_hud7be1fef60d7ca79fe62725cd577b339_23547_3dbb13ff34ddc76002709c53ec51a078.webp 400w,
               /post/geco_at_egu2023/qr_hud7be1fef60d7ca79fe62725cd577b339_23547_3d24883e367880aa4a2c3e5efac47656.webp 760w,
               /post/geco_at_egu2023/qr_hud7be1fef60d7ca79fe62725cd577b339_23547_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos_3.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://geco-group.org/post/geco_at_egu2023/qr_hud7be1fef60d7ca79fe62725cd577b339_23547_3dbb13ff34ddc76002709c53ec51a078.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;250&#34;
               height=&#34;760&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;
      QR-Code to this blog post.
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A Song of Carbon And Nitrogen: Part 1 - The Setting</title>
      <link>https://geco-group.org/post/song-cn/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Jan 2023 22:37:04 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://geco-group.org/post/song-cn/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;part-1---the-setting&#34;&gt;Part 1 - The Setting&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Have you ever looked at a forest and wondered about where all this wood comes from? Like all plants, trees have the magnificent capability to draw gaseous carbon dioxide from the air and turn it into hard touchable wood. But trees do not only need carbon to grow. Like humans, they need other nutrients to build their leaves, stems, and roots. A major nutrient to do so is nitrogen - another element well hidden from our eyes that actually makes up about 80% of our earth&amp;rsquo;s atmosphere.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unlike carbon dioxide, however, trees do no take up nitrogen through their leaves. Quite the opposite, in fact! They often rely on a tight friendship with tiny microorganisms that live attached or even within their roots. These microorganisms can access nitrogen through various ways, like absorbing it directly from the atmosphere, breaking up old plant debris, or even by chewing away on pieces of rocks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Looking at all the trees growing around us, one may think that the acquisition of carbon and nitrogen cannot be that complicated - trees seem to do it all the time, right? And yet, the current state of knowledge shows that this is no trivial question at all. And luckily so! This complex and fascinating interplay of our ecosystem&amp;rsquo;s carbon and nitrogen cycle is my PhD&amp;rsquo;s main research topic. This blog post is the beginning of what I call &amp;ldquo;A Song of Carbon and Nitrogen&amp;rdquo;, with obvious cultural reference to the great fantasy story.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All research must be founded on a grand overarching question that embodies its relevance for our life. Understanding the carbon-nitrogen cycle is of great interest because it directly affects our biosphere&amp;rsquo;s capability of coping with human-made climate change. More carbon dioxide and a warmer climate may sound nice for plants, and indeed the biosphere&amp;rsquo;s carbon uptake has increased over the past decades&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But for how long will this be the case? Unfortunately, we just don&amp;rsquo;t know. Once plants are limited by nutrient availability, they no longer help us tackle climate change. In fact, the IPCC&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:2&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; estimates that the feedback of the biosphere to rising CO2 (think of this feedback as &amp;ldquo;how much plants slow down climate change&amp;rdquo;) ranges from a strong negative feedback (this is good, plants take up a lot of carbon) to almost no feedback at all (this is bad, plants don&amp;rsquo;t help no more)&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:3&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:3&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, how can we calm our minds and find out whether plants (hopefully) continue to help us out? That is the grand challenge of my PhD. The song of carbon and nitrogen tells the story of each carbon and nitrogen atom. How trees take each of them up through air and soil, how they march through life and death as they bloom as leaves and decay as litter, how they get another chance at life thanks to tiny soil microbes that restart their life from anew. Who follows, and who leads? Who pushed and who drags?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The interactions of the carbon-nitrogen cycle are highly interwoven, complex to understand, and a mystery we need to solve to comprehend what may happen to our precious planet under the pressure of climate change. Although I have not yet settled on a precise formulation, the grand question of my PhD may sound something like this: What are the complex interactions of the carbon and nitrogen cycle in our ecosystems that determine whether the global biosphere will continue to aid us in our fight against climate change?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Disclaimer: This blog post is part of Pascal&amp;rsquo;s PhD journey and was originally published &lt;a href=&#34;https://padasch.netlify.app/posts/2023-01-12_ascan_part1_setting/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;footnotes&#34; role=&#34;doc-endnotes&#34;&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:1&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;See Section 5.4.3 Climate Effect on Land Carbon Uptake in Chapter 5 of IPCC AR6 (&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ipcc.ch/report/ar6/wg1/chapter/chapter-5&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Link&lt;/a&gt;)&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:2&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;IPCC: Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:3&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;See Figure 5.29b (land carbon response to CO2) in Chapter 5 of IPCC AR6 (&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ipcc.ch/report/ar6/wg1/figures/chapter-5&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Link&lt;/a&gt;)&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:3&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
