<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>postdoc | Geocomputation and Earth Observation</title>
    <link>https://geco-group.org/tag/postdoc/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://geco-group.org/tag/postdoc/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>postdoc</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Mon, 01 May 2023 08:46:40 +0100</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://geco-group.org/media/logo_hue21406914225b119becd577af1fb7f4d_583632_300x300_fit_lanczos_3.png</url>
      <title>postdoc</title>
      <link>https://geco-group.org/tag/postdoc/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Postdoc in drone-based vegetation water stress monitoring</title>
      <link>https://geco-group.org/joinus_old/postdoc_uav/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 May 2023 08:46:40 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://geco-group.org/joinus_old/postdoc_uav/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Our group for Geocomputation and Earth Observation develops new model and data integration methods to gain a mechanistic understanding of the terrestrial biosphere. We are hosted at the Geography Institute of the University of Bern and work at the intersection of Earth system science, remote sensing, ecology, and hydrology.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This position serves to establish and consolidate near-range remote sensing capacities in our research group and integrate field-based research within the context of our research on drought impact monitoring and prediction.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;tasks&#34;&gt;Tasks&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You will plan and perform a drone-based surface reflectance remote sensing campaign for water stress detection in Swiss forests. You will analyse data and lead publications on vegetation water stress relations across landscape-scale gradients.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;requirements&#34;&gt;Requirements&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The candidate must hold a Ph.D. degree in a relevant field. Experience in drone-based remote sensing with completed training in the operation of UAVs, ideally with license, experience in managing field campaigns, and experience with close-range remote sensing data post-processing are required. The candidate should demonstrate proficient English written and oral skills. We expect a collaborative mentality and enthusiasm for the development of our computational infrastructure and open-source software.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;we-offer&#34;&gt;We offer&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We offer the candidate to be part of a growing group with a strong collaborative philosophy and and a tight international network of leading partners, providing further career development opportunities toward future academic or industry positions. You will benefit from a supporting academic environment and from the attractive quality of life in Switzerland.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We look forward to receiving your online application including the following documents: Motivation letter (max. 2 pages, with a statement of research interests and demonstrated experience with software development projects), a CV, copies of academic qualifications and the names and e-mail addresses of three referees. Please note that we exclusively accept applications submitted through our online application portal. Applications via email or postal services will not be considered. We continue recruitment until a suitable candidate is found. The start of this position is at your earliest convenience. The position is offered for one year with possibility for continuation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Questions regarding the position should be directed to Dr. Koen Hufkens (&lt;a href=&#34;mailto:koen.hufkens@giub.unibe.ch&#34;&gt;koen.hufkens@giub.unibe.ch&lt;/a&gt;) (no applications). You can apply for this position by following &lt;a href=&#34;https://ohws.prospective.ch/public/v1/redirect/ebd3c469-7556-435a-9857-c9a4e8f717eb/ats/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;THIS LINK&lt;/a&gt; to the online submission platform.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
