<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Join us - Open positions and thesis topics | Geocomputation and Earth Observation</title>
    <link>https://geco-group.org/joinus/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://geco-group.org/joinus/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Join us - Open positions and thesis topics</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Thu, 16 Jan 2025 08:36:01 +0100</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://geco-group.org/media/logo_hue21406914225b119becd577af1fb7f4d_583632_300x300_fit_lanczos_3.png</url>
      <title>Join us - Open positions and thesis topics</title>
      <link>https://geco-group.org/joinus/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Master thesis - Hyperspectral imaging of vegetation</title>
      <link>https://geco-group.org/joinus/hyperspec/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 16 Jan 2025 08:36:01 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://geco-group.org/joinus/hyperspec/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Context:&lt;/strong&gt; Drone-based yperspectral imaging of vegetation has the potential to identify plant water stress across the landscape. It is hypothesised that at this scale, effects by limited moisture availability in the rooting zone are not evenly distributed and potentially relate to topographic gradients and vegetation-groundwater connectivity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Aim:&lt;/strong&gt; The aim of this thesis is to perform a pilot campaign for a one-time assessment of the spectral property of the surface reflectance in a forest near Bern, relating patterns to species identity and their position in the landscape.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Methods:&lt;/strong&gt; Drone-based hyperspectral images and LiDAR data processing and analysis.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Requirements:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Basic understanding of remote sensing.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Experience working with R or other data science tools is a prerequisite.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The student writes the thesis in English.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Supervision:&lt;/strong&gt; Dr. Yousra El-Mejjaouy and Prof. Benjamin Stocker&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Postdoc - Next Generation Bern Earth System Model</title>
      <link>https://geco-group.org/joinus/postdoc_bern3dlpx/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Dec 2024 08:36:01 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://geco-group.org/joinus/postdoc_bern3dlpx/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The University of Bern is seeking a highly motivated postdoctoral researcher for a two-year position in Earth System Modeling with a focus on land vegetation dynamics, jointly hosted by the Climate and Environmental Physics division at the Institute of Physics and the Institute of Geography and affiliated with the Oeschger Centre for Climate Change Research.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This exciting opportunity focuses on the coupling and development of the Earth System Model of Intermediate Complexity Bern3D and the Dynamic Global Vegetation Model LPX-Bern. The successful candidate will play a crucial role in advancing the models and our understanding of Earth system processes and their interactions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;tasks&#34;&gt;Tasks&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Improve integration between Bern3D and LPX-Bern models to simulate fully coupled feedbacks between land, atmosphere, ocean, and ice sheets.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Quantify and identify feedbacks and tipping points in the climate system.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Validate model results against paleoclimate data and perform simulations of future climate scenarios.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Contribute to ongoing international collaborations, including the Tipping Point Model Intercomparison project (TIPMIP).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Produce high-quality scientific publications.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You will actively contribute to the new groups on Global Biogeochemical Modeling (Dr. Frerk Pöppelmeier) and Geocomputation and Earth Observation (Prof. Benjamin Stocker), presenting results at international scientific conferences and publishing in the peer-reviewed literature.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;requirements&#34;&gt;Requirements&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The successful candidate holds a PhD degree in Climate or Earth Science, Physics, or a related field, or will have obtained the degree before the start of the project. The candidate should have a deep interest in climate modeling and possess advanced programming skills (e.g., in Python, Fortran, R, Julia) and data handling skills. Additionally, the candidate should have a passion for interdisciplinary and collaborative research and be proficient in both written and spoken English. Knowledge of dynamical vegetation modeling is an advantage.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;we-offer&#34;&gt;We offer&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This project offers the opportunity to work with experts in past and future climate modeling, proxy reconstructions, and land vegetation dynamics, providing an inspiring environment for Early Career Scientists in this field. The candidate will be part of a network of climate scientists across institutes and departments within the Oeschger Centre for Climate Change Research.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The envisaged starting date is 1st March 2025 or upon agreement. Employment conditions and remuneration are in accordance with the standards of the University of Bern, Switzerland. The initial appointment is for two years, with the potential for extension.
For further information please contact Dr. Frerk Pöppelmeier (&lt;a href=&#34;mailto:frerk.poeppelmeier@unibe.ch&#34;&gt;frerk.poeppelmeier@unibe.ch&lt;/a&gt;) and/or Prof. Benjamin Stocker (&lt;a href=&#34;mailto:benjamin.stocker@unibe.ch&#34;&gt;benjamin.stocker@unibe.ch&lt;/a&gt;).
All applications received before 14th January 2025 will be reviewed, and further applications will be considered until the position is filled. Please send your application documents in a single PDF-file including a motivation letter, CV, degree certificates, and contact information for two references by e-mail to Dr. Frerk Pöppelmeier (&lt;a href=&#34;mailto:frerk.poeppelmeier@unibe.ch&#34;&gt;frerk.poeppelmeier@unibe.ch&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Master thesis - LGM-Holocene vegetation dynamics</title>
      <link>https://geco-group.org/joinus/lgmveg/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Sep 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://geco-group.org/joinus/lgmveg/</guid>
      <description>&lt;!-- 

&lt;div class=&#34;alert alert-note&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div&gt;
    Click on the &lt;strong&gt;Slides&lt;/strong&gt; button above to view the built-in slides feature.
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
 --&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Context&lt;/strong&gt;: Vegetation dynamics and the land carbon cycle can now be modelled more realistically thanks to a new generation of demography-resolving vegetation models. The succession of vegetation types since the Last Glacial Maximum, as reconstructed paleo-climatic archives, provides a perfect test for these models’ hindcasts of vegetation change and thus also their forecasts of vegetation responses to future climate change.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Aim&lt;/strong&gt;: Model parameterisations for dominant European plant species will be developed and multi-millennial model simulations evaluated against vegetation reconstructions from lake sediments in the Alpine region.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Methods&lt;/strong&gt;: BiomeEP, paleo-climate simulation outputs, model parameterisation and evaluation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Main supervision:&lt;/strong&gt; Prof. Dr. Benjamin Stocker
&lt;strong&gt;Co-supervision:&lt;/strong&gt; Prof. Willy Tinner, Dr. Christoph Schwörer&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Master thesis - Unlocking the power of tree-ring data for modelling forest carbon dynamics</title>
      <link>https://geco-group.org/joinus/treerings/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Sep 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://geco-group.org/joinus/treerings/</guid>
      <description>&lt;!-- 

&lt;div class=&#34;alert alert-note&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div&gt;
    Click on the &lt;strong&gt;Slides&lt;/strong&gt; button above to view the built-in slides feature.
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
 --&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Context&lt;/strong&gt;: Tree-ring data is available in spades but has only marginally been used in the context of climate impacts on the land carbon cycle.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Aim&lt;/strong&gt;: This project will develop methods to use information of annual tree-ring anomalies for constraining modelled tree growth and forest dynamics in response to climate variability.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Methods&lt;/strong&gt;: Vegetation modelling (BiomeEP model) and model-data evaluation and calibration.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Main supervision:&lt;/strong&gt; Prof. Dr. Benjamin Stocker
&lt;strong&gt;Co-supervision:&lt;/strong&gt; Dr. Stefan Klesse, WSL Birmensdorf&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Master thesis - Sink vs. source control on tree growth</title>
      <link>https://geco-group.org/joinus/sinksource/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 Sep 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://geco-group.org/joinus/sinksource/</guid>
      <description>&lt;!-- 

&lt;div class=&#34;alert alert-note&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div&gt;
    Click on the &lt;strong&gt;Slides&lt;/strong&gt; button above to view the built-in slides feature.
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
 --&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Main supervision:&lt;/strong&gt; Prof. Dr. Benjamin Stocker
&lt;strong&gt;Co-supervision:&lt;/strong&gt; Dr. Antoine Cabon, WSL Birmensdorf&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Forests currently represent a large carbon sink, offsetting a quarter of human CO2 emissions each year, bur large uncertainty remains on the future strength of this sink. Namely, vegetation models assume that tree growth is essentially limited by photosynthesis, but recent evidence suggests that currently unaccounted for biophysical limitations to tree growth by low temperatures and water stress can substantially decouple tree growth from photosynthesis. The degree to which biophysical limitations might slow down forest carbon storage is still unclear but has potentially critical implications for climate projections.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The objective of this project is to implement biophysical limitations to tree growth in an established mechanistic vegetation model in order to quantify the effect of these new controls on forest primary production. This will require (1) designing the integration of fine scale biophysical equations with carbon-based tree growth schemes of the vegetation model, (2) evaluating model performance against annual and decadal observations of historical tree growth and forest production across Europe and (3) simulate forest production using current and new tree growth schemes to evaluate the impact of biophysical limitations on forest production under different climate scenarios.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This thesis is a great starting point for mechanistic ecosystem modelling and working with large datasets of the terrestrial biosphere. Basic knowledge of programming are a requirement and prior experience with R and/or Fortran are an advantage. You may start as soon as you like. Please contact me directly if you’re interested.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This Master project is part of the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.wsl.ch/de/projekte/micss-physiological-drivers-of-tree-growth.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;MiCSS project&lt;/a&gt;, led by &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.wsl.ch/de/mitarbeitende/cabonant.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Dr. Antoine Cabon, WSL Birmensdorf&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Bachelor or Master thesis - High resolution quantification of seasonal water deficits</title>
      <link>https://geco-group.org/joinus/hires_cwd/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 Feb 2024 08:46:40 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://geco-group.org/joinus/hires_cwd/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;background&#34;&gt;Background&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Seasonal water deficits, caused by the imbalance of water from the land surface through evapotranspiration and runoff and the gain through precipitation, are an important driver of agricultural productivity and forest growth. Recent research by our group (Stocker et al., 2023) has revealed large spatial heterogeneity of seasonal water deficits across the globe at 5 km resolution - interpreted as a reflection of (otherwise unobservable) rooting zone water storage capacity across the soil and bedrock and of plant access to the groundwater, and as a reflection of water use in cropland areas.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;aim&#34;&gt;Aim&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Novel data resources from &lt;a href=&#34;https://etdata.org/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;OpenET&lt;/a&gt; now provide analysis-ready data at field-scale resolution. This provides an opportunity to extend the analysis of Stocker et al. (2023) to the hillslope-scale. You will develop a workflow to access cloud-hosted Earth Observation data and perform analyses for deriving cumulative water deficits. This will generate crucial insights for a better understanding of the role of terrain in shaping plant water availability and for informing land managers about the sustainability of water resource use.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;requirements&#34;&gt;Requirements&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Most important: High motivation to work on questions related to land-atmosphere exchange and the carbon cycle - everything else can be learned!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Confidence to work with large datasets of the terrestrial biosphere.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Experience working with R or other data science tools are an advantage.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The student writes the thesis in English.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;supervision&#34;&gt;Supervision&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Prof. Benjamin Stocker&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Master thesis - Global land carbon cycle modelling</title>
      <link>https://geco-group.org/joinus/global_biomee/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 Feb 2024 08:38:39 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://geco-group.org/joinus/global_biomee/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;background&#34;&gt;Background&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dynamic Global Vegetation Models (DGVMs) are key tools for understanding biosphere-climate feedbacks and transient vegetation dynamics in response to global change. A novel vegetation demography model, the BiomeE, is a mechanistic cohort-based model which simulates vegetation dynamics and biogeochemical processes. This mechanistic model is able to simulate the size dependent competition, and thereby links plant functional traits, physiology, forest demography and stand dynamics. The GECO group has developed of a new framework for modelling of terrestrial biosphere processes (&lt;a href=&#34;https://geco-bern.github.io/rsofun/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;rsofun&lt;/a&gt;) that combines the BiomeE model with a photosynthesis model using optimality principles (P-model). This framework has been used to run site-level simulations in different regions, including boreal, temperate and tropical forests. Still, a global simulation capturing global patterns, has not carried out yet, but will be the basis for our future research on the global carbon cycle, potentially leading to participation in simulation activities for the Global Carbon Project. This thesis is an ideal entry point for your work in this direction.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /media/global_biomee_hu1fc26a5764c71c7ad2dd83d1c5d21ac2_1475022_0bb60b5e0ba5bc3736229262bfa4750c.webp 400w,
               /media/global_biomee_hu1fc26a5764c71c7ad2dd83d1c5d21ac2_1475022_f30e2bdc15bb137e41da1b24a5282103.webp 760w,
               /media/global_biomee_hu1fc26a5764c71c7ad2dd83d1c5d21ac2_1475022_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos_3.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://geco-group.org/media/global_biomee_hu1fc26a5764c71c7ad2dd83d1c5d21ac2_1475022_0bb60b5e0ba5bc3736229262bfa4750c.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;760&#34;
               height=&#34;288&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Above: Prescribed global distribution of plant functional types. Figure from &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.5194/gmd-15-8153-2022&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Weng et al., 2022&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;aim&#34;&gt;Aim&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Develop a wrapper for pixel-wise (parallelised) rsofun calls, given a path to global forcing files, as an R package.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Run BiomeE with P-model.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Preparations for Global Carbon Project simulations&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;requirements&#34;&gt;Requirements&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The student is motivated to work and contribute to the development of a new modelling framework.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Experience working with R or other data science tools are a prerequisite.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Basic understanding of mathematical modelling and a keen interest to delve deeper into modelling and programming (R)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The student writes the thesis in English.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;literature&#34;&gt;Literature&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Weng, E. S., Malyshev, S., Lichstein, J. W., Farrior, C. E., Dybzinski, R., Zhang, T., Shevliakova, E., and Pacala, S. W. 2015: Scaling from individual trees to forests in an Earth system modeling framework using a mathematically tractable model of height-structured competition, Biogeosciences, 12, 2655–2694, &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.5194/bg-12-2655-2015&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://doi.org/10.5194/bg-12-2655-2015&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Weng, E., Dybzinski, R., Farrior, C. E., and Pacala, S. W. 2019: Competition alters predicted forest carbon cycle responses to nitrogen availability and elevated CO2: simulations using an explicitly competitive, game-theoretic vegetation demographic model, Biogeosciences, 16, 4577–4599, &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.5194/bg-16-4577-2019&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://doi.org/10.5194/bg-16-4577-2019&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Stocker, B. D., Wang, H., Smith, N. G., Harrison, S. P., Keenan, T. F., Sandoval, D., Davis, T., and Prentice, I. C. 2020: P-model v1.0: an optimality-based light use efficiency model for simulating ecosystem gross primary production, Geosci. Model Dev., 13, 1545–1581, &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.5194/gmd-13-1545-2020&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://doi.org/10.5194/gmd-13-1545-2020&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Weng, E., Aleinov, I., Singh, R., Puma, M. J., McDermid, S. S., Kiang, N. Y., Kelley, M., Wilcox, K., Dybzinski, R., Farrior, C. E., Pacala, S. W., and Cook, B. I. 2022: Modeling demographic-driven vegetation dynamics and ecosystem biogeochemical cycling in NASA GISS&amp;rsquo;s Earth system model (ModelE-BiomeE v.1.0), Geosci. Model Dev., 15, 8153–8180, &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.5194/gmd-15-8153-2022&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://doi.org/10.5194/gmd-15-8153-2022&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;supervision&#34;&gt;Supervision&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Dr. Laura Marqués&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Prof. Benjamin Stocker&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Bachelor or Master thesis - Indentifying frost events and impacts in ecosystem flux measurements</title>
      <link>https://geco-group.org/joinus/frost_gpp/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 Feb 2024 08:24:51 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://geco-group.org/joinus/frost_gpp/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Supervision:&lt;/strong&gt; Prof. Benjamin Stocker, &lt;strong&gt;Co-supervision:&lt;/strong&gt; Dr. Laura Marqués, Dr. Yann Vitasse (WSL Birmensdorf)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;background&#34;&gt;Background&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Climate warming is driving an advance of leaf unfolding in trees, promoting longer growing seasons. However, the advance of the start-of-the-season (SOS) can induce &lt;em&gt;false springs&lt;/em&gt;, i.e., a stretch of unexpectedly warmer temperatures in late winter/early spring followed by sudden freezing events. These frost events after the SOS can affect the structure and function of terrestrial ecosystems and have important environmental and economic consequences. Still, there is little consensus on how frost events change under global warming and the implications. Therefore, it is relevant to understand the occurrence of frost events once the growing season has started and how they change among regions in temperate and boreal forests.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;aim&#34;&gt;Aim&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The goal of this project is to identify when the frost events happen after the SOS and quantify their impact on carbon fluxes. The student will characterize the SOS using phenological measurements and ecosystem-level photosynthesis (gross primary production, GPP). Daily minimum temperatures will be used to calculate the number of frost events. The project design includes combining ground observations, eddy covariance flux measurements, remote sensing data and global climate datasets.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If addressed as a MSc topic, there is a possiblity for a publication as a thesis outcome.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;requirements&#34;&gt;Requirements&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The student is motivated to work with large datasets of the terrestrial biosphere.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Experience working with R or other data science tools are an advantage.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The student writes the thesis in English.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;literature&#34;&gt;Literature&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Chamberlain,  C.J., Cook, B.I., Morales-Castilla, I. and Wolkovich, E.M. (2021).  Climate change reshapes the drivers of false spring risk across European trees. New Phytol, 229: 323-334.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Liu,  Q., Piao, S., Janssens, I.A. et al. (2018). Extension of the growing season increases vegetation exposure to frost. Nat Commun 9, 426 .&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Hufkens,  K., Friedl, M.A., Keenan, T.F., Sonnentag, O., Bailey, A., O&amp;rsquo;Keefe, J. and Richardson, A.D. (2012). Ecological impacts of a widespread frost event following early spring leaf-out. Glob Change Biol, 18: 2365-2377.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Piao, S, Liu, Q, Chen, A, et al. (2019). Plant phenology and global climate change: Current progresses and challenges. Glob Change Biol. 25: 1922– 1940.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
