<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>GPP | Geocomputation and Earth Observation</title>
    <link>https://geco-group.org/tag/gpp/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://geco-group.org/tag/gpp/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>GPP</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Wed, 21 Feb 2024 08:32:52 +0100</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://geco-group.org/media/logo_hue21406914225b119becd577af1fb7f4d_583632_300x300_fit_lanczos_3.png</url>
      <title>GPP</title>
      <link>https://geco-group.org/tag/gpp/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Bachelor thesis - Importance of GPP extremes in eddy covariance data</title>
      <link>https://geco-group.org/joinus/gpp_extremes/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 Feb 2024 08:32:52 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://geco-group.org/joinus/gpp_extremes/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;background&#34;&gt;Background&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The gross primary production (GPP) of an ecosystem, that is, the carbon it assimilates via photosynthesis, differs strongly from one year to the next. This variability between years is called the interannual variability (IAV) of GPP and the reasons for why GPP can change substantially from year to year are unclear. From a global scale analysis, we know that the seasonal cycles in precipitation and temperature in semi-arid ecoystems contribute substantially to the global IAV of GPP, highlighting the role of water and heat. We also know that even a few unusual hours in a total year can contribute disproportionately more to an ecosystems annual carbon uptake. For example, just 2% of unusually hot hours can account for ca. 10% of an ecosystems’ total annual GPP. Considering an increase in frequency and intensity of extreme events under climate change, a better quantification and characterisation of GPP extremes is crucial to estimate the future global carbon balance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;aim&#34;&gt;Aim&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The goal of this project is to quantify the role of GPP extremes on an ecosystem’s carbon uptake, using FLUXNET data (half-hourly measured land-atmosphere exchange of carbon dioxide). The first aim is to identify years that show GPP extremes, that is, anomalies in their annual total GPP. Then, a suitable method to assess the effect of extreme days within these anomalous years on the year’s total GPP is explored by (e.g., using a Gini index). Further questions may cover investigating the difference across globally distributed sites or comparing observed against modelled GPP to identify the drivers of GPP extremes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;requirements&#34;&gt;Requirements&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Most important: High motivation to work on questions related to land-atmosphere exchange and the carbon cycle - everything else can be learned!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Confidence to work with large datasets of the terrestrial biosphere.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Experience working with R or other data science tools are an advantage.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The student writes the thesis in English.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;literature&#34;&gt;Literature&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ahlström A, Raupach MR, Schurgers G, Smith B, Arneth A, Jung M, Reichstein M, Canadell JG, Friedlingstein P, Jain AK, &lt;em&gt;et al.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;strong&gt;2015&lt;/strong&gt;. The dominant role of semi-arid ecosystems in the trend and variability of the land CO 2 sink. &lt;em&gt;Science&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;348&lt;/strong&gt;: 895–899.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Kannenberg SA, Bowling DR, Anderegg WRL&lt;/strong&gt;. &lt;strong&gt;2020&lt;/strong&gt;. Hot moments in ecosystem fluxes: High GPP anomalies exert outsized influence on the carbon cycle and are differentially driven by moisture availability across biomes. &lt;em&gt;Environmental Research Letters&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;15&lt;/strong&gt;: 054004.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Launiainen S, Katul GG, Leppä K, Kolari P, Aslan T, Grönholm T, Korhonen L, Mammarella I, Vesala T&lt;/strong&gt;. &lt;strong&gt;2022&lt;/strong&gt;. Does growing atmospheric CO 2 explain increasing carbon sink in a boreal coniferous forest? &lt;em&gt;Global Change Biology&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;28&lt;/strong&gt;: 2910–2929.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Wieder WR, Butterfield Z, Lindsay K, Lombardozzi DL, Keppel‐Aleks G&lt;/strong&gt;. &lt;strong&gt;2021&lt;/strong&gt;. Interannual and Seasonal Drivers of Carbon Cycle Variability Represented by the Community Earth System Model (CESM2). &lt;em&gt;Global Biogeochemical Cycles&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;35&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;supervision&#34;&gt;Supervision&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Prof. Benjamin Stocker&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Bachelor or Master thesis - Indentifying frost events and impacts in ecosystem flux measurements</title>
      <link>https://geco-group.org/joinus/frost_gpp/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 Feb 2024 08:24:51 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://geco-group.org/joinus/frost_gpp/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Supervision:&lt;/strong&gt; Prof. Benjamin Stocker, &lt;strong&gt;Co-supervision:&lt;/strong&gt; Dr. Laura Marqués, Dr. Yann Vitasse (WSL Birmensdorf)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;background&#34;&gt;Background&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Climate warming is driving an advance of leaf unfolding in trees, promoting longer growing seasons. However, the advance of the start-of-the-season (SOS) can induce &lt;em&gt;false springs&lt;/em&gt;, i.e., a stretch of unexpectedly warmer temperatures in late winter/early spring followed by sudden freezing events. These frost events after the SOS can affect the structure and function of terrestrial ecosystems and have important environmental and economic consequences. Still, there is little consensus on how frost events change under global warming and the implications. Therefore, it is relevant to understand the occurrence of frost events once the growing season has started and how they change among regions in temperate and boreal forests.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;aim&#34;&gt;Aim&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The goal of this project is to identify when the frost events happen after the SOS and quantify their impact on carbon fluxes. The student will characterize the SOS using phenological measurements and ecosystem-level photosynthesis (gross primary production, GPP). Daily minimum temperatures will be used to calculate the number of frost events. The project design includes combining ground observations, eddy covariance flux measurements, remote sensing data and global climate datasets.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If addressed as a MSc topic, there is a possiblity for a publication as a thesis outcome.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;requirements&#34;&gt;Requirements&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The student is motivated to work with large datasets of the terrestrial biosphere.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Experience working with R or other data science tools are an advantage.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The student writes the thesis in English.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;literature&#34;&gt;Literature&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Chamberlain,  C.J., Cook, B.I., Morales-Castilla, I. and Wolkovich, E.M. (2021).  Climate change reshapes the drivers of false spring risk across European trees. New Phytol, 229: 323-334.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Liu,  Q., Piao, S., Janssens, I.A. et al. (2018). Extension of the growing season increases vegetation exposure to frost. Nat Commun 9, 426 .&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Hufkens,  K., Friedl, M.A., Keenan, T.F., Sonnentag, O., Bailey, A., O&amp;rsquo;Keefe, J. and Richardson, A.D. (2012). Ecological impacts of a widespread frost event following early spring leaf-out. Glob Change Biol, 18: 2365-2377.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Piao, S, Liu, Q, Chen, A, et al. (2019). Plant phenology and global climate change: Current progresses and challenges. Glob Change Biol. 25: 1922– 1940.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A constraint on historic growth in global photosynthesis due to rising CO2</title>
      <link>https://geco-group.org/publication/keenan-23-natcc/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Nov 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://geco-group.org/publication/keenan-23-natcc/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>An effective machine learning approach for predicting ecosystem CO$_textrm2$ assimilation across space and time</title>
      <link>https://geco-group.org/publication/debartolomeis-23-egu/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Sep 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://geco-group.org/publication/debartolomeis-23-egu/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
